<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truths in a true light, or, A pastoral letter to the reformed Protestants in Barbados vindicating the Non-Conformists from the misrepresentations commonly made of them, in that island and other places : and demonstrating that they are indeed the truest and soundest part of the Church of England / from Francis Mackemie.</title>
            <author>Mackemie, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M308</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31151</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11781020</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11781020</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49055</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49055)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1487:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truths in a true light, or, A pastoral letter to the reformed Protestants in Barbados vindicating the Non-Conformists from the misrepresentations commonly made of them, in that island and other places : and demonstrating that they are indeed the truest and soundest part of the Church of England / from Francis Mackemie.</title>
                  <author>Mackemie, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the successors of Andrew Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinbvrgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Postscript, p. 25-38.</note>
                  <note>Dated, p. 24 : Barbados, December 28, 1697.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Barbados.</term>
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49055:1"/>
            <p>TRUTHS In a true LIGHT. OR, A Paſtoral LETTER, to the Reformed Proteſtants, IN BARBADOS</p>
            <p>Vindicating the <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> from the Miſrepreſentations, commonly made of them, in that Iſland, and in other places: AND, Demonſtrating, That they are indeed the <hi>trueſt and ſoundeſt part of the Church of</hi> ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>From, <hi>Francis Mackemie,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Pet. 3.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beloved, Seeing ye know theſe things before, beware—Leſt ye fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH.</hi> Printed by the Succeſſors of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49055:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49055:2"/>
            <head>Truths in a true Light.</head>
            <head type="sub">An Epiſtle, To the Reformed PROTESTANTS of <hi>Barbados.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT has been too notorious, what Diabolical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and baſe Plots the Emiſſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> have contrived, promoted, and attempted, to over throw that Glorious work, and cauſe of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> or to lead or cajole us back into our anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Slavery, Idolatry, and Superſttion; and for Effectuating thereof, they have not been wanting, neither have ſtuck at any thing, to widen our <hi>breaches,</hi> augment our <hi>Differences,</hi> hinder our mutual Condeſcentions, and our endeavoured Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations, raiſing implacable heats, and keeping us aſunder by Diſtinguiſhing <hi>Characters,</hi> and Diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating <hi>Names;</hi> ſetting up <hi>contrary Intereſts;</hi> and often raiſing violent Storms of bitter <hi>Perſecutions,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigating the <hi>Aſcendent</hi> Party, ſtill to trample upon the <hi>Non-Con's,</hi> and by all means to render them black, and odious; and all this, and much more, to ruin <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and weaken the <hi>Protestant Intereſt.</hi> And it deſerves to be bewailed, that in all their Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49055:3"/>Intrigues and evil deſigns, they ſoon found too many <hi>Proteſtant Tools,</hi> unadviſedly to concur with ſuch ſworn Enemies of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> too much whereof appeared in the late Reigns; &amp; I wiſh there may not be found among us ſtill, too many <hi>Incendiaries,</hi> to raiſe Diſſentions, and ſtir up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Heats, among <hi>Reformed Protestants,</hi> that we may become a prey ſtill to the <hi>Common Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God, for our ſeaſonable, and happy <hi>Revolution,</hi> that has in a great meaſure broke the deep projects, of that <hi>Jeſuitical Party;</hi> and by an Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed <hi>Liberty,</hi> to all <hi>Diſsenting Proteſtants,</hi> has bound the Hands of former Perſecutors. I wiſh the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Spirit,</hi> and Inclination, were gone too; and that many unawares were not promoting, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging again, the old Malice, and grand Deſigns of the common Enemy, by their Tongues, in railing, reproaching, and decrying, a great part of the <hi>purest Reformation,</hi> under the Diſcriminating names of <hi>Presbyterian, Puritan, Fanatick, Calviniſt,</hi> and what not? And how many are <hi>ſimply led away,</hi> by a hot, violent party, and ſuffer themſelves to be impoſed upon, who know not the matters of our leſſer Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and ſay little againſt <hi>Intolerable Popery,</hi> and the moſt dangerous Haereticks, but all their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Venom, is ſpewed out and levelled againſt their <hi>Proteſtant Brethren,</hi> of the <hi>ſame Reformation,</hi> and of the ſame Kingdom; and yet ſeem to be in Charity with the <hi>ſame particular Profeſſion</hi> in other parts of the World.</p>
            <p>All who ſtudy Hiſtories of the <hi>Proteſtant Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> may be aſſured, that the <hi>Reformed Church of England,</hi> conſiſted all along of <hi>two ſorts</hi> of men;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49055:3"/>firſt, many <hi>Sober,</hi> Moderate, Sound, and Tender men, who never were for <hi>Perſecution</hi> of <hi>Protestants,</hi> and would willingly have parted with many <hi>unſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Ceremonies</hi> for the Churches Peace, and gaining <hi>Diſsenters;</hi> and the <hi>Seed</hi> or <hi>Root</hi> of theſe have been from the <hi>Original</hi> of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and abounded in the Reigns of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and K <hi>J I.</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and were <hi>Anti-arminian,</hi> and faithful to the <hi>firſt Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Articles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and continued the <hi>prevailing party,</hi> until the Reign of <hi>Ch.</hi> the <hi>I.</hi> There was alſo another, hot, and <hi>Violent party,</hi> who were ready to brand the Sober, and Serious of their own Church, as <hi>Puritans, Preciſians,</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> betrayed their own <hi>Articles,</hi> embraced <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> and grew more zealou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>Rites,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> than for the <hi>Eſsentials,</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantials</hi> of Religion; crying up <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> and <hi>Conformity,</hi> more than true <hi>Christianity;</hi> acting <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra-Canon,</hi> and inſtead of coming farther from <hi>Rome,</hi> by a further <hi>Reformation,</hi> which our <hi>firſt Reformers</hi> deſigned, and the <hi>moderate party</hi> deſired; they both in <hi>Doctrine, Practice</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> made ſeveral <hi>advances</hi> towards <hi>Rome,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> ſometimes Hiſtory-Profeſſor of <hi>Oxford,</hi> relates in his <hi>Short History</hi> thereof; which <hi>advances</hi> gave Popes and Papiſts no ſmall hopes of <hi>Englands</hi> return to <hi>Rome,</hi> as a Jeſuit affirms, ſhewing the changes in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and its affinity to <hi>Rome,</hi> for, he ſaith, <hi>The Doctrine is altered</hi> in many things; The <hi>Pope</hi> is no longer <hi>Anti chriſt: Images</hi> are tollerated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination</hi> on <hi>fore ſeen works: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Grace: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent Righteouſneſs,</hi> are all granted: <hi>Free-Will</hi> is Preached up: they have given to the 39. Articles
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49055:4"/>a <hi>Catholick ſence:</hi> they acknowledge the Authority of the <hi>Church</hi> in deciding <hi>Controverſies,</hi> about matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> and interpretation of Scripture: they make frequent uſe of the more venerable Names of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Altars;</hi> and to be a <hi>Calviniſt</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> is to be a <hi>Traitor,</hi> and a <hi>Heretick,</hi> or worſe; to which may be added, bowing to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar;</hi> and ſetting up <hi>unlighted Candles</hi> in Churches, which Dr <hi>Warmestry,</hi> one of their own ſpoke againſt, and ſaid, That they were a <hi>fit Emblem</hi> of our Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and unprofitable Clergy, which filled up the <hi>Candlesticks</hi> of the Churches, but gave <hi>no Light.</hi> And this party was Rampant in <hi>Lauds</hi> time, who had a party of Monſtrous tools, as <hi>Montague, Heilin, Poc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>nton, Dow, Couzins, Shelford, Beel, Stafford, Watts,</hi> and <hi>Fedder,</hi> of no ſmall figures; with many more, who under their own hands, Publiſh'd <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and down-right <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctrines, and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical and enſlaving <hi>Maxims of State,</hi> and were ſo countenanced, and protected by the <hi>King,</hi> and ſome of the <hi>Court,</hi> that they carried all before them, and it was no ſmall Crime for any to ſpeak againſt their Romiſh <hi>Innovations,</hi> and Intollerable <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations,</hi> both in Church and State, as in the Cruel unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and Illegal puniſhments inflicted on ſome of their own Communion, until their Deſigns were ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably oppoſed &amp; checked, by ſuch of their Church who were ſincere, and uncorrupted, when backt by Lords and Commons Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the year 1640 complaining in bold ſpeeches of thoſe that went after the <hi>Romiſh Way:</hi> and though <hi>Laud</hi> had juſtly meted to him what he meaſured out to others, which gave a conſiderable blow to his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49055:4"/>party, and by that Revolution of Affairs, greatly fruſtrated the hopes of <hi>Rome,</hi> who were filled with great Expectations of <hi>Changes,</hi> by their Agents and Deputies in <hi>England;</hi> and though many ſuffer of almoſt Twenty years abducation from the Pulpits, during the <hi>Civil Wars;</hi> yet it is to be feared the Seed and Spawn of this <hi>faction,</hi> has been growing ſince in the Church, and ſo prevailing a party, as were able to obſtruct that Union, accommodation and <hi>Comprehenſion,</hi> deſigned between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Diſsenters,</hi> firſt by a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from our moſt Gracious KING, and late Gracious QUEEN, and next by a <hi>Convocation,</hi> who had but very ſmall regard to their Majeſties <hi>Supremacy</hi> in Eccleſiaſticks, and who ſo vigorouſly oppoſed what they had ſo lately addreſſed their Majeſties for.</p>
            <p>I ſhould gladly embrace an opportunity to inform ſuch of you, as have never been in <hi>Europe,</hi> what <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Diſsenters</hi> are; who ſuffer your ſelves to be ſtrangely impoſed on, &amp; know little more of them, but miſrepreſentations &amp; calumnies thrown upon them, by malitious Ignorant and ill-minded men, as if they were <hi>Monſters,</hi> and moſt inſufferable in Church and State; though they are a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of the <hi>Proteſtant Reformation,</hi> agreeing in all points of Faith, and Divine Ordinances, or parts of Worſhip, with the Eſtabliſht Church of <hi>England;</hi> and the likeſt to them of any Proteſtants, differing only in <hi>Ceremonies, Government</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> of which I ſhall hint a little in this Epiſtle. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>Scotland,</hi> they were the <hi>first Reformers</hi> of that Kingdom from Popery, though originally by mean and inconſiderable men, and in oppoſition to a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49055:5"/>ſtrong <hi>Court party,</hi> and not only <hi>without,</hi> but <hi>againſt</hi> the Authority of the State, which demonſtrated the more of the hand of Divine Providence therein. And notwithſtanding all their ſtrugglings with <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Praelacy;</hi> which in the late Reigns have been obtruded upon them, contrary to <hi>Oaths, Laws,</hi> and repeated <hi>Eſtabliſhments</hi> of that Kingdom; yet they went a greater length in Reformation, than their Neighbours in <hi>England,</hi> who upon prudential Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations retained ſome <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> leaſt it ſhould be dangerous to Reform all at once, as <hi>Scotland</hi> did. And in that Kingdom <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are now the <hi>Establiſhed Church,</hi> and thoſe of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> there, are the <hi>Diſsenters,</hi> and have far leſs Reaſon for it, than we in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to thoſe of <hi>England,</hi> they were from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning a part of the <hi>Engliſh Reformation;</hi> for the beſt Hiſtories inform us, thoſe who chiefly had the firſt managment of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> were divided into <hi>two Claſses,</hi> much what equal in number, and quality of Intereſt. Some of them, as Biſhop <hi>Hooper, Coverdale, John Fox, John Rogers,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> appeared vigorouſly for an <hi>abſolute and thorough Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> according to the Model <hi>Calvin</hi> had given of it, and ſo it would have been a <hi>Presbyterian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;</hi> but others, as <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Cox,</hi> and others were peremptorily of the Judgment, that a <hi>Reformation in all points at first,</hi> would be of dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence, and that at once to <hi>reform all,</hi> would be to <hi>reform none at all;</hi> and though the Judgment of the latter prevailed, yet all approved of the former as <hi>best,</hi> tho' ſome approved not the <hi>jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi> as <hi>ſeaſonable,</hi> until the People who were almoſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49055:5"/>all <hi>Papists,</hi> were better inſtructed and diſpoſed to receive the impreſſions of this intire, and <hi>perfect Reformation;</hi> therefore they were left not without hopes of a <hi>further Reformation,</hi> from their Poſterity and Succeſſors, which we were aſſured of by a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the Preface to <hi>old Common Prayer Books,</hi> but left out of the <hi>new.</hi> And ſo it was <hi>for that time</hi> agreed on, that for the better gaining of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſome <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> and a great part of the <hi>Roman Service,</hi> were to be kept. Thus both <hi>parties</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred and united in hopes of a <hi>further Reformation,</hi> until the bloody <hi>Marian</hi> Perſecution under which ſome of both Claſſes fell and dyed <hi>Martyrs,</hi> others became Refugees abroad; and upon their return, inſtead of a <hi>further Reformation, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity Acts</hi> were promoted, and paſſed in the firſt of <hi>Eliz.</hi> Yet during the Lives of ſome good Biſhops, and for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years, no <hi>Subſcription,</hi> nor uſe of all the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer,</hi> nor an exact obſervance of the <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> was urged; until <hi>Whitgift</hi> aſcended the Chair, whoſe zeal for <hi>Ceremonies</hi> was boldly impugned by Learned <hi>Cartwright.</hi> And now, Subſcription and <hi>Conformity</hi> was required, under penalty of <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> and <hi>Deprivation,</hi> and <hi>John Fex</hi> the Martyrologer, required to Subſcribe, who refuſed, pulling out of his Pocket his <hi>Greek Teſtament,</hi> and told the Arch-Biſhop, <hi>He would ſubſcribe nothing but That:</hi> Yet his gravity and good Service to the Church protected him, that he dyed quietly in a low Station in the Church. But when he perceived the retaining the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> did not attain the <hi>first Deſign of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> in gaining <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and ſaw the miſchief, the impoſing of them on <hi>Protestants,</hi> was like to do,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49055:6"/>he afterwards ſaid of them, <hi>God take them from us, or us from them!</hi> Harder things were ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and impoſed, to the caſting out of many able and godly Miniſters, followed by multitudes of People; and theſe being caſt out, and kept out to this day, are <hi>Non conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Diſsenters,</hi> and the moſt conſiderable part <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Ireland</hi> are partly from <hi>England,</hi> partly from <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who ſince the Conqueſt joyned with others in Settling that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And as to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and forreign Churches, they are either <hi>Calvinists</hi> or <hi>Lutherans:</hi> But all the <hi>Calviniſt</hi> Churches as lately of <hi>France, Geneva, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Piedmont,</hi> and many other places of high and low <hi>Germany,</hi> are <hi>Presbyterians:</hi> The <hi>Lutherans</hi> differ from us both in many things, and indeed are much degenerated from <hi>Luthers</hi> primitive though imperfect <hi>Reformation:</hi> So that by all computation, <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> with ſuch as are in full Communion with them, are the <hi>greater part,</hi> and from the Judgment of our <hi>firſt Reformers,</hi> are the <hi>better part</hi> of the <hi>Reformation;</hi> the <hi>Church of England</hi> not excepted, whoſe <hi>Reformation</hi> is not yet <hi>intire</hi> and <hi>perfect,</hi> as you may learn from the Preface to the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and from the K. and Qs. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for a <hi>further Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that you may more fully and diſtinctly know them, and not ſuffer your ſelves for the future to be impoſed upon; I ſhall as one of the meaneſt of them, ſhew what at this day they <hi>believe &amp; do;</hi> or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they <hi>agree,</hi> and are the ſame, with the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Church of England;</hi> and next what they <hi>diſsent</hi> from,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49055:6"/>and neither <hi>will</hi> nor <hi>dare</hi> do, without Sin; and all this only for your Information, without the leaſt deſign or intention, of raiſing any <hi>new debate,</hi> on beginning any Controverſy on thoſe differences, ſufficiently Controverted by many hands on both ſides.</p>
            <p>And firſt, I ſhall inform you, what they <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>do,</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whereby every ſerious and intelligent Reader, may readily perceive two things 1. That we are <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Brethren,</hi> and in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with them in the main, great and <hi>Subſtantial</hi> points of the Chriſtian and Proteſtant Religion; and therefore deſerve not to be treated, as many Ignorantly do, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in this Iſland. 2. That of all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that differ from them, we differ in the <hi>leaſt</hi> and <hi>ſmalleſt</hi> matters. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They receive and believe the <hi>Bible,</hi> the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> to be the Word of God, from the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate inſpiration of Heaven, and in its original, and its Orthodox Tranſlations, they univerſally embrace it, as the compleat and full <hi>Rule</hi> of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> and the <hi>only Directory</hi> in all matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They believe and receive, as agreeable to their <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> in all the <hi>Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Articles,</hi> except ſuch as relate to <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> which the Eſtabliſhment of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom obliges them not to Subſcribe, receiving the 3d Article in a Ptoteſtant ſenſe; and this ſo qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>moſt,</hi> if not <hi>all</hi> their Miniſters, have <hi>Subſcribed</hi> as a condition of their Eſtabliſhed <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49055:7"/>
            <p n="3">3. They believe, own, maintain and perform all <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>parts</hi> of Gods <hi>Inſtituted Service</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> in Publick, Private and Secret, that are mentained &amp; profeſſed by any <hi>Reformed Protestants,</hi> as Preaching, Praying, Reading, Hearing, Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Singing of Pſalms, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They firmly believe, and ſtrenuouſly hold, a fixed and ſtanding <hi>Ministry</hi> to be always in the Church, <hi>to the End of the World;</hi> and Churches to be furniſhed with all <hi>Officers</hi> warranted in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, duly <hi>qualifyed</hi> and orderly <hi>ſet apart,</hi> according to the Word of God; and after a long and moſt ſtrict Examination and tryal, ſome are allowed firſt to <hi>Preach</hi> only as <hi>Probationers,</hi> or <hi>Expectants</hi> for a proof of their Preaching gifts, and Praying abilities, and of a Holy Converſation; and when called to the <hi>Pastoral Charge,</hi> ſubmitting to a ſecond Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, they are orderly ſet apart or <hi>Ordained</hi> to the <hi>whole Work of the Miniſtry;</hi> according to the Apoſtles phraſe, by <hi>the Impoſition of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. They abhor, renounce and abjure <hi>Popery,</hi> Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, Superſtition and Haereſy, with every Error, they are convinced and perſwaded is contrary to the Word of God; univerſally believing the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be the <hi>Grand Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. They hold and maintain an Authoritative <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Order, Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Cenſure,</hi> committed by Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>Head of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church,</hi> unto <hi>Church Officers</hi> appointed by him, conſiſting in <hi>Admonition, Suſpenſion</hi> &amp; <hi>Excommunication;</hi> and this Government ſpecifically diſtinct from all <hi>Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:49055:7"/>
            <p n="7">7. They <hi>Baptiſe</hi> both <hi>Adult</hi> Perſons, &amp; <hi>Children</hi> of believing Parents, profeſſing the Truth of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="8">8. They believe, and always maintain the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallity of the <hi>Fourth Commandment,</hi> and perpetuity of a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> with the ſtrict obſervation of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> wholly to be employed and ſpent in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, Private and Secret Service, and Worſhip of God, allowing works of abſolute <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>Mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. They conſcientiouſly and faithfully keep and obſerve, all <hi>Solemn Days,</hi> and occaſional Times, ſet apart upon extraordinary, and emergent Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, for Humiliation, <hi>Faſting &amp; Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. Though they abhor as much as any, all vain <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Curſing,</hi> yet they maintain and allow the Lawfulneſs, of Witneſſing to Truth, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of Falſhood by a <hi>Solemn Oath,</hi> when called thereunto by a <hi>Lawful Magistrate,</hi> in matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; tho' they rather like to do it, after the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Pattern, with a <hi>Solemn lifting up of the Hand to Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. They hold and maintain <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Civil Government,</hi> to be an Ordinance of God; and many of them highly Zealous for <hi>Monarchy,</hi> as in <hi>Scotland, England, France</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> though others in <hi>Geneva, Holland</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> are for <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of thoſe places.</p>
            <p n="12">12. They are highly for <hi>School-Education</hi> and Learning, and Academical accompliſhments, for fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and preparing men in an ordinary way, for <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Offices</hi> in the Church; not excluding, but including <hi>particular Gifts,</hi> and Qualifications, and a <hi>Call</hi> from God to that great Work.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49055:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> They are the ſame in theſe, and moſt things material, with the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> therefore beware of Reproaching <hi>Presbyterians</hi> as the <hi>worst;</hi> as <hi>bad</hi> if not worſe than <hi>Papists;</hi> leaſt ye wound &amp; reflect upon your ſelves; unto whom they are likeſt of any other Diſſenters, that are <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Now though we <hi>agree</hi> in all theſe things and more, yet we <hi>differ</hi> or <hi>diſsent</hi> in three or four Things, to all which I ſhall ſpeak, branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the particulars, as far as an Epiſtolary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication will allow of. 1. In <hi>Common Prayer</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> 2 In your <hi>Canons.</hi> 3. In your <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> or <hi>Praelacy.</hi> 4. In your <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Cenſures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I</hi> I ſhall begin with <hi>Common Prayer</hi> and <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;</hi> and concerning them, we differ in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, waving many of our <hi>Reaſons,</hi> to avoid <hi>Offence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. We dare not receive nor comply with ſtinted Compoſed and Impoſed <hi>Forms,</hi> or <hi>Lyturgies</hi> of Worſhip, becauſe not <hi>Commanded</hi> nor <hi>Warranted</hi> by the Word of God, nor known in the pureſt and Original Centuries of the <hi>Goſpel Churches,</hi> but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed without <hi>Divine Commiſſion,</hi> and required meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>Men,</hi> in the <hi>Degenerate</hi> and <hi>latter Ages</hi> of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though we <hi>deny not</hi> altogether, but <hi>allow</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Forms of Prayer</hi> on many Caſes, as ſtudyed Forms for ones-ſelf, and Compoſed eaſy and plain Forms for the <hi>Ignorant</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskillful,</hi> as young ones, early Converts, as Crutches for the Weak and Lame; yet we cannot nor dare not, <hi>Ordain</hi> and call any man to be a <hi>Minister</hi> of the Goſpel, and to take
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49055:8"/>
               <hi>Charge of Souls,</hi> that hath not given ſufficient proof, and demonſtration of their <hi>Praying</hi> and <hi>Preaching</hi> Gifts and Abilities at all Times, and ſuitably or pertinently for all occaſions and conditions, without <hi>preſcribed Forms</hi> read in a Book; and we never denyed the Lawfulneſs of joyning with the ſound Words of others in Prayer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such Miniſters as have received of God, and have given ſufficient <hi>Proof</hi> to many, of their <hi>Praying</hi> Gifts and Abilities, dare not ordinarily, and in their ordinary Adminiſtrations, tye themſelves to, and only uſe theſe preſcribed and <hi>Book Forms,</hi> leaſt they ſhould be guilty of not uſing and improving, but hiding or burying their <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Talents,</hi> and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the Character of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Servants</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. We dare not <hi>read</hi> as a part of Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the <hi>Aphocrypha</hi> Books, which are enjoyned and read, ſeeing they are acknowledged by all, not to be <hi>Canonical</hi> Scripture, and owned by many, and in many things falſe and fabulous; eſpecially, while we have the <hi>Scripture</hi> by us, that <hi>Perfect Rule</hi> of Faith and manners.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We cannot nor dare not allow in Publick Worſhip, which (ſhould be for the Edification of all) that <hi>inarticulate,</hi> and <hi>unintelligible</hi> way and noiſe, of the People, all or moſt <hi>confuſedly ſpeak together,</hi> one mans voice drowning the accent of another, which ſeems to be ſo far from <hi>Order,</hi> that it appears <hi>confuſion,</hi> as <hi>Service in an unknown Tongue. Hicker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingill</hi> tells us, he ſuffers no ſuch babling in his Church at <hi>All Saints</hi> in <hi>Colchester,</hi> as is made by <hi>alternate Reſponſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. We cannot allow <hi>Women</hi> to ſpeak in the Church,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49055:9"/>as many of <hi>yours,</hi> in your <hi>whole Service,</hi> talk more in a Day, than ſome <hi>Quaker-Women,</hi> condemned by <hi>most</hi> for that practice.</p>
            <p n="7">7. We dare not add to the Sacrament of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> an airy Sign of the <hi>Croſs</hi> that <hi>periſhes with the uſing,</hi> more than <hi>Spittle, Oyl</hi> and <hi>Salt;</hi> nor allow the <hi>Spiritual Signification</hi> impoſed by men, and explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the 30th. Canon; Seeing <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ſignifies all that and more; and <hi>you</hi> own in the <hi>Form</hi> for <hi>private Baptiſm,</hi> that it is valid and ſufficient without it. And further it is abuſed at this Day to <hi>Idolatry</hi> in <hi>Romiſh Churches; Cranmers</hi> great Argument for aboliſhing <hi>Images</hi> out of the <hi>Churches,</hi> though <hi>ſome</hi> are got in again; and moſt of them into their <hi>Book</hi> of Devotion.</p>
            <p n="8">8. We cannot comply with that <hi>Popiſh posture</hi> (not our <hi>Saviours poſture</hi>) of <hi>Kneeling at the Lords Supper,</hi> which cannot be more Reverent, nor ſo ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to a <hi>Table Feaſt,</hi> as <hi>his</hi> was; and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> was originally a conſequence of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and came in with it 1200. years after our Saviour, and was a <hi>ſtumbling block</hi> to many <hi>Reformed Proteſtants,</hi> highly reſented by <hi>Beza,</hi> and many more, and proved ſo grateful to Papiſts, that <hi>Bonner</hi> having learned that <hi>Cranmer</hi> and <hi>Ridley</hi> had kept <hi>this,</hi> (and other Ceremonies) ſaid, <hi>that he doubted not, ſince their Broth went down with them ſo well, that er'e long they ſhould eat of their Beef too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. We cannot, we dare not in <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> exclude the <hi>Parents</hi> from engaging and promiſing in behalf of their own Children, and take in other <hi>Sureties,</hi> whom <hi>all know,</hi> and <hi>none expect,</hi> they will endeavour to <hi>perform</hi> what they <hi>promiſe</hi> and undertake; which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49055:9"/>indeed is impoſſible for any to perform, eſpecially when more <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and more <hi>Irreligius Sureties</hi> are called in than the <hi>excluded Parents,</hi> as Papiſts, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and prophane Perſons, Strangers, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Young Children,</hi> which we apprehend to be a willful promoting of known perfidiouſneſs, and a down-right <hi>mocking of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 Becauſe we find the <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> in its ſeveral parts tranſlated out of ſeveral <hi>Popiſh Books;</hi> the <hi>Frayers</hi> are taken out of the <hi>Breviary,</hi> the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of <hi>Sacraments, Burial, Matrimonies,</hi> and <hi>Viſiting of the Sick,</hi> are taken out of the <hi>Romiſh Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall;</hi> the Conſecration of the <hi>Lords Supper, Collects, Epistles and Goſpels,</hi> are taken out of the <hi>Maſs Book;</hi> (though ſome things are left out, as <hi>Prayers</hi> to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> Saints and Angels:) This is to us, one juſt prejudice againſt the uſe of it.</p>
            <p n="11">11. We cannot away with, nor dare we aſſent to, nor believe, many things and ſayings in the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> nor uſe that <hi>Corrupt Tranſlation</hi> of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> while God has provided us with a better, we dare not pretend the imitation of our Saviours <hi>Miraculous Feaſt</hi> by that Popiſh and <hi>Mock-Feaſt of Lent,</hi> conſiſting not in <hi>abſtinence</hi> but in <hi>chooſing of Meats</hi> In, <hi>Te Deum,</hi> we dare not ſay, <hi>all the Earth worſhip thee,</hi> while we are aſſured the greateſt part are <hi>Infidels</hi> to this Day, and neither <hi>Worſhip</hi> nor <hi>know</hi> the true God; we dare not aſſent to the Damning Sentence of <hi>Athenaſius</hi>'s Creed which many of the <hi>Elderſons</hi> of your Church wiſhed it never had been in <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi> We dare not ſay, <hi>Every perſon Baptiſed is immediately Regenerated;</hi> for ſo all Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed ſhould be Saved. We dare not <hi>alter, add to,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49055:10"/>and <hi>diminiſh from</hi> the Scriptures, the Word of God, as the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>corrupt Tranſlation</hi> of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> does; particularly, we cannot conſent to the taking away of the <hi>Scripture Titles</hi> of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> given from Immediate Inſpiration, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Popiſh and Lattine Titles in their Room; In the <hi>Burial of the Dead,</hi> we dare not call every one, whether we know them or not, <hi>our dear Siſter or Brother,</hi> and as a part of Publick Worſhip ſay, <hi>We have a ſure and certain Hope of their Reſurrection, unto eternal Life;</hi> and to make no difference between the <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>Godly;</hi> a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> once Baptiſed, and a ſerious <hi>Christian;</hi> allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the <hi>ſame Charity</hi> and <hi>Character,</hi> ſeems an encouragement to <hi>ungodlineſs,</hi> and a diſcouragement to <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. Though we are for <hi>Viſiting,</hi> Inſtructing, convincing, admoniſhing, praying for, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the <hi>Sick,</hi> according as we find their ſtate and condition, various and different, Yet we apprehend the <hi>Burial Service</hi> to be Symbolizing with <hi>Rome,</hi> and no part of God's Publick Worſhip, or any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded part of a <hi>Miniſters Work,</hi> and though it is ſaid, It has no relation to the <hi>dead</hi> at all, but only for the Edification of the <hi>Living,</hi> why was it denyed to the Living at the Funeral of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Henry Vaughan?</hi> why is it deny'd to the <hi>Living</hi> at the Funeral of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbaptiſed,</hi> and <hi>Excommunicated</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? Why is it read oft times when the <hi>People</hi> are <hi>gone,</hi> except two that remain to cover the <hi>Corps?</hi> Why do the <hi>deceaſed perſons</hi> pay for it? and lately there was a poor man, to whom it was denyed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>unbaptiſed? Actions</hi> with vulgar People, are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49055:11"/>more demonſtrative, than <hi>Words.</hi> And what Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication does that afford to the <hi>Living,</hi> that is read at the entry of the <hi>Church yard,</hi> of which few or none hear one Word? and why is not all either read in the <hi>Desk,</hi> or at the <hi>Grave?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> The <hi>Second</hi> thing wherein we diſſent from you is, your <hi>Canons,</hi> which few of your ſelves <hi>obey</hi> and <hi>obſerve,</hi> no, not ſuch as have <hi>Sworn Obedience</hi> to them. They are moſt <hi>Arbitrary Decrees,</hi> (when not ratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Authority;) not at all ſuitable to the ſtate of the <hi>Church;</hi> neither dare we take the <hi>Oath of Aſsent and Conſent,</hi> that they contain <hi>nothing contrary to the Word of God,</hi> while both you and we are otherwiſe perſwaded.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> A Third thing wherein we diſſent, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church by <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Chauncellors, Commiſsaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Arch Deacons, &amp;c.</hi> as not have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foundation in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> nor the Government of the <hi>Goſpel-Churches,</hi> nor agreeable to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>first Centuries</hi> after our Saviour. And though we are for <hi>Scripture Biſhops</hi> both name and office, and wiſh with Dr. <hi>Wild</hi> in his poetical flight, <hi>Where there is one, there were ten;</hi> neither would refuſe the Government of the firſt two or three hundred years after our Saviour; and it is known moſt of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>England</hi> oſtered to embrace Dr. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> his model of <hi>Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> yet there are ſeveral things in which <hi>we</hi> diſſent, and which many of <hi>yours</hi> diſlike in Engliſh or <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Praelacy;</hi> as,</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:49055:12"/>
            <p n="1">1. Creating &amp; Erecting <hi>new Offices</hi> &amp; <hi>Officers,</hi> beſides what Chriſt gave to and Inſtituted in his Church, the Names whereof are not ſo much as known or mentioned in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Promoting <hi>Praeeminence,</hi> and deſtroying that <hi>Miniſterial Parity,</hi> our Saviour Commanded, and Inouſtriouſly maintained in his days, for bidding all <hi>Maſtery and Dominion</hi> over one another.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their aſſeming high and <hi>Lordly Titles,</hi> and <hi>Temporal Dignities,</hi> and <hi>Civil places,</hi> being advanced above moſt Peers and States men: This was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to good Old <hi>Latimer,</hi> who in a Sermon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed King <hi>Ed.</hi> 6 to <hi>untord</hi> all the <hi>Lordly Biſhops,</hi> and remove them from all their <hi>Temporal Offices and Employments,</hi> that <hi>they might follow their Spiritual Plough Tail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Their frequenting the <hi>Court,</hi> attending the <hi>Council Table,</hi> and ſitting in <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to the great neglect of their <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Work,</hi> being above <hi>Preaching, Praying</hi> and Adminiſtring of <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and <hi>Church Government</hi> too; therefore a <hi>Non Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Biſhop,</hi> called a <hi>Preaching Biſhop, a Preaching Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb.</hi> And what prejudice would it be to the <hi>State,</hi> but what a great advantage to the <hi>Church,</hi> if the Government ſaw it meet to revive again, that old vote of a <hi>Church of England Parliament,</hi> recorded in <hi>Bakers</hi> Chronicles, <hi>That no Biſhop ſhould have any Vote in Parliament, nor any Judicial power, in the Star Chamber, nor bear any ſway in Temporal Affairs, and that no Clergy man ſhould be in the Commiſſion of the Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Their Graſping at a <hi>larger Charge</hi> over many great Congregations of a <hi>Vaſt Dioceſs,</hi> whereby an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49055:12"/>
               <hi>Epiſcopal Charge,</hi> and care can no more be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or Diſcharged in the ſight of God, (As over the Dioceſs of <hi>London,</hi> and all <hi>Engliſh Plantations;</hi> while ſo much Time is ſpent at <hi>Court,</hi> and in ſecular affairs,) than the <hi>Italian Biſhop</hi> can be <hi>Metropolitan</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 Though they have <hi>Forms</hi> preſcribed for many things, yet no Forms nor Directions, for tryal and examination of <hi>Candidates</hi> or <hi>Expectants,</hi> for <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> to the Miniſtry; For turning one of the 39 Articles into Latin, and proving it from Scripture, is already done to their hands; ſo that any Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian or School Boy may do it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IV</hi> Laſtly, We diſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt from the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and though they are without all <hi>Church Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Cenſure</hi> in every Plantation of <hi>America;</hi> yet as it is managed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> many of your <hi>own Sons</hi> diſlike it, as well as <hi>we;</hi> eſpecially in theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Its <hi>abſoluteneſs;</hi> being exerciſed by a ſole Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the breaſt of a <hi>particular Dioceſan,</hi> acting all in <hi>his own name,</hi> without Commiſſion or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from any other; and Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> who was highly for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> tells us, the Biſhop gives orders <hi>alone,</hi> excommunicates <hi>alone,</hi> and affirms it to be <hi>without Example</hi> in all good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; for Kings and Monarchs have their <hi>Councellours,</hi> the Courts of <hi>Kings bench, Common Pleas,</hi> and <hi>Exchequer,</hi> have <hi>many Judges;</hi> and the <hi>Chancellor</hi> hath the aſſiſtance of 12 <hi>Maſters of Chauncery.</hi> And I am aſſured, the Scripture warrant is directed to a <hi>number, Dic Eccleſiae, tell the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49055:13"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Authority &amp; Power of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally managed by <hi>Delegation,</hi> or <hi>Deputation</hi> of <hi>Lay Perſons,</hi> as <hi>Chauncellours, Officials, Regiſters, Sumners, Canonists</hi> &amp;c. chooſing ſuch as <hi>helps in Government,</hi> rather than the <hi>Clergy,</hi> which the Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> affirms to be <hi>contrary to all rules of good Government;</hi> for Offices of confidence and skill, cannot be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed by <hi>Deputies;</hi> the confidence and truſt being <hi>Perſonal</hi> and <hi>Inhaerent,</hi> cannot be tranſpoſed to an ignorant, and unqualifyed <hi>Lay-Perſon,</hi> more than ſuch can be <hi>deputed,</hi> to <hi>Preach the Word, and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister the Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Engliſh <hi>Church-Diſcipline</hi> is turned into a meer <hi>Money matter,</hi> and the uſe of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Keyes is made <hi>Mercenary,</hi> puniſhing the <hi>Purſes,</hi> and not afflicting the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of the Delinquents; as a great man of the Church, in a Sermon Preached at one of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> told them, <hi>Claves Chriſti pulſant crumenas, non verberant Conſcientias</hi> And <hi>Hickringale</hi> aſſures us from his certain knowledge, that <hi>Guinea's</hi> will procure <hi>Abſolutions</hi> from Drs <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> without any <hi>Confeſſion</hi> or ſhew of <hi>Repentance;</hi> yea, without a <hi>ſight</hi> of the <hi>guilty party;</hi> a more bare-faced practice than of the <hi>Romiſh Churches,</hi> who always uſe <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Pennance</hi> for a <hi>Cloak.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope theſe things will engage you to be more favourable and charitable to <hi>Diſsenters,</hi> until you more rationally weigh and confider the grounds and reaſons of their <hi>Diſsent,</hi> for they may ſometimes and in ſome caſes be the <hi>purer</hi> &amp; <hi>better</hi> part of a <hi>Nation;</hi> as the Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and in all their other Captivities were <hi>Diſsenters:</hi> The three
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49055:13"/>worthies in <hi>Daniel</hi> were <hi>Diſsenters</hi> in <hi>Babylon;</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> under <hi>Darius,</hi> was a <hi>Diſsenter.</hi> Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, all his <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> with their Chriſtian followers, were <hi>Diſsenters,</hi> until <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Reign; and all Chriſtians in <hi>Mahometan</hi> Dominions, and <hi>Pagan</hi> Countries all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in Popiſh Countries; and your ſelves in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all forreign parts, are <hi>Diſsenters;</hi> and it were hard and uncharitable to condemn <hi>all</hi> theſe as <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi> In favour of ſome <hi>Diſsenters,</hi> I ſhall only lay down one ſaying from your <hi>Hale</hi> of <hi>Schiſm, All pious aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies in times of perſecution and corruption, are the only lawful Congregations, and the publick Aſsemblies, though according to form of Law, are indeed nothing but Riots and Conventicles, if ſtained with Corruption and Superstition</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let us ſtill value and eſteem <hi>unity</hi> in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and the greater and more weighty matters, preferring it before an exact and accurate <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> in every <hi>Punctilio</hi> of <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,</hi> and <hi>Ceremony,</hi> which <hi>no Nation</hi> hath hitherto attained, the <hi>Church of England</hi> not excepted; for what uniformity is between your <hi>Cathedral</hi> and <hi>Parochial</hi> Worſhip? between ſuch Churches as have <hi>Organs,</hi> and thoſe that want them? between ſuch as <hi>Sing,</hi> or <hi>Chant</hi> the <hi>Service,</hi> and ſuch as do not? between ſuch as read the <hi>whole Service,</hi> and others that <hi>Mince</hi> it, and read but a part? between thoſe that begin with a <hi>free Prayer,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>do not?</hi> And in the ſame Congregations, what Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity is between ſuch as uſe <hi>Reſponſes,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>do not?</hi> between ſuch as <hi>Bow</hi> to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> or the <hi>Altar,</hi> and ſuch as <hi>do not?</hi> between ſuch as <hi>bow the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49055:14"/>knee,</hi> and thoſe that only <hi>bow the head,</hi> at the Name or Word, <hi>Jeſus.</hi> What <hi>uniformity</hi> between ſuch as <hi>Sing Pſalms,</hi> and moſt that <hi>do not?</hi> And I find ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Sons</hi> of the Church, break <hi>uniformity,</hi> and <hi>Canons,</hi> as well as their Neighbours: what <hi>uniformity-act,</hi> or <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> allows any to begin with a <hi>Prayer of their own,</hi> as the greateſt and beſt have done, though others call it a <hi>Geneva trick?</hi> What uniformity-act enjoins <hi>Organs,</hi> and <hi>Singing Boyes:</hi> and where is bowing to the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Altar,</hi> with all other <hi>Church Honours,</hi> commanded? What war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants the uſe of the <hi>publick Form</hi> for <hi>private Baptiſm?</hi> why is the <hi>burial Service</hi> read over any <hi>Diſsenters,</hi> that are all <hi>excommunicated</hi> by your <hi>Canons?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me humbly and earneſtly, with all Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion addreſs the <hi>conformable Clergy,</hi> in this Iſland, to inſtruct their People, that <hi>they</hi> and <hi>we</hi> profeſs the ſame Chriſtian and <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> only with ſome alterations in external <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances;</hi> that we may unite in affection and ſtrength, againſt the <hi>common Enemy</hi> of our Reformation, and concur in the great work of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for the manifeſtation of Gods Glory, and the Conviction, Converſion and Salvation of Souls in this Iſland, inſtructing ſuch as are Ignorant, in the principal &amp; great things of Religion, promoting vertue and true holineſs, and Preaching down and reproving all Atheiſm, irreligion, and profanity, ſealing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming all by an univerſal <hi>Copy,</hi> pattern and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of a holy, and Miniſterial Life and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</p>
            <p>I have often done it, and I continue to Pray for the zealous concurrence of the <hi>Secular power,</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49055:14"/>
               <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> to whom the <hi>Sword of Juſtice</hi> is committed, for the <hi>terrour of the Evil doers, and praiſe of thoſe that do well,</hi> that for promoting a viſible Reformation in this Iſland, from the Evils that have long expoſed us to the heavy Judgments of a Righteous God, they would <hi>first reform their own Lives,</hi> and impartially execute theſe <hi>Good Laws,</hi> according to their <hi>Oaths,</hi> againſt all <hi>Blaſpheming, Curſing, Swearing, Whoredom, Sabbath breaking,</hi> all <hi>Prophanity, Impiety and Irreligion,</hi> that our <hi>Land may be exalted by Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> may no longer be our <hi>Reproach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Candid Reader,</hi> They frequently charge <hi>Diſsenters</hi> that when <hi>others</hi> are the <hi>Aſcendent,</hi> they cry out againſt <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and for <hi>Moderation;</hi> but when they are <hi>uppermoſt,</hi> they are as ſevere as any; The <hi>former</hi> is natural for all men, that when they are maſtered, or like to be conquered, they cry out for <hi>Quarter,</hi> and plead <hi>moderation,</hi> as we find the <hi>Church of England,</hi> ſhewed as much of it as any, when there was occaſion, and ground for it. What conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſions and <hi>fair promiſes</hi> did they allow K. <hi>Charles II.</hi> to make, yea, and to take the <hi>Coronation Oath of Scotland,</hi> to maintain <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> there, and alſo to give Solemn Proteſtations at <hi>Breda,</hi> to Diſſenters of <hi>England,</hi> confirmed by a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for Liberty to all tender Conſciences?</hi> but ſoon after the Reſtoration, all was violated and ſoon forgot. The next time they were under any fears, was at the Diſcovery of the <hi>Grand Popiſh Plot,</hi> and freſh pretences for <hi>moderation</hi> were then Publiſhed; but continued not long, ending in a <hi>Sham plot,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49055:15"/>a <hi>new Perſecution</hi> And the next trouble the Church of <hi>England</hi> was in, was when the <hi>Seven Biſhops</hi> were in the Tower, only for refuſing to engage upon their Honours to anſwer at the <hi>K Bench,</hi> to what ſhould be objected againſt them; and then in their Petition to the late K they profeſſed a great deal of <hi>tenderneſs to Diſsenters;</hi> and about the time of the Prince of O. his landing, all their Diſcourſe was of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſion;</hi> and afterwards confirmed it by an <hi>Addreſs,</hi> and their Majeſties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to endeavour an Agreement, between the <hi>Church of England</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Diſsenters;</hi> and in adhering to his Royal Promiſe and deſign, firſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Diſſenters an <hi>eſtabliſhed Liberty,</hi> and ſoon after iſſued forth a <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> founded on the <hi>Preface to the Common Prayer;</hi> which the <hi>Convocation,</hi> after they were ſecured and ſafe from their late fears and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, took no further notice of, but in oppoſition to all their lately profeſſed <hi>tenderneſs,</hi> refuſed to part with <hi>one indifferent Ceremony,</hi> in obedience to their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Authority,</hi> or for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with Diſsenters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the God of all Grace, would bleſs the World with a better Spirit, is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sirs,</salute> 
               <signed>Your devoted Servant in all Civility, <hi>FRANCIS MACKEMIE.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Barbades,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>December</hi> 28. 1697.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49055:15"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>AMong the miſrepreſentadons of the principles and practices of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in this Iſland. I cannot for bear taking ſpecial notice of one; becauſe it ſtrikes ſo very deep into the Vitals of Religion: 'Tis, that the Doctrine of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation,</hi> as taught by the rigid <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k of <hi>Scotland,</hi> is contrary to the Word of God, and a great diſcouragement to Piety. Tho' I owe not my <hi>birth,</hi> but a part of my <hi>Education</hi> only to that Kingdom, yet having read many of their <hi>Books,</hi> heard ſeveral of their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years, on all Doctrines of the <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> and having alwayes with me, their <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> their <hi>Catechiſms,</hi> with many found and excellent Treatiſes; I do profeſs my ſelf fully of <hi>their</hi> Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in <hi>this,</hi> and all other Doctrines of Faith, and in Gods ſtrength ſhall never ſwerve nor prevaricate: And in their behalf do profeſs and declare, they hold no <hi>Predestination,</hi> but what is maintained in all the <hi>Calviniſt, Reformed Churches</hi> abroad, and by all the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and further, the ſame which is held and maintained by the <hi>Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiſhed Church of England.</hi> If I prove this, I hope you will own they have been palpably miſrepreſented; And that I may effectually and undenyably do it, I ſhall firſt lay down the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> both from their <hi>Catechiſms,</hi> and <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> In their Shorter <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> learned &amp; taught by many in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49055:16"/>teach, <hi>That the Decrees of God, are the eternal Counſel of his will, whereby for his own Glory he hath foreor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained whatſoever comes to paſs.</hi> In their <hi>larger Catechiſm,</hi> they are ſome-what fuller, and teach, <q>that the Decrees of God are the wiſe, free and holy acts of the Counſel of his Will, whereby from all Eternity, he hath for his own Glory, unchangeably foreordained whatſoever comes to paſs in time, eſpecially concerning Angels and Men:</q> And in the following Q they further teach, <q>That God by an eternal and immutable Decree, out of his meer Love, for the Praiſe of his Glorious Grace, to be manifeſted in due time, hath Elected ſome Angels to Glory, and in Chriſt hath choſen ſome men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Eternal Life, and the means thereof, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Sovereign power, and the unſearchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Counſel of his Will, whereby he extendeth or with holdeth favour as he pleaſeth, hath paſſed by and fore-ordained the reſt to diſhonour and wrath, to be for their Sin inflicted, to the praiſe of his Juſtice.</q> And what is for our purpoſe in their Confeſſion of Faith, is this: — 3d. Parag. <q>By the Decrees of God, for the manifeſtation of his Glory, ſome Men and Angels are Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated unto everlaſting Life, and others ſore-ordained to everlaſting Death. 4. Thoſe Angels and Men thus predeſtinated &amp; fore ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to everlaſting Life, are particularly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably deſigned, and their number ſo certain, and definite, that it cannot be either encreaſed or diminiſhed. 5. Thoſe of mankind that are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated unto Life, God before the Foundation of the World was laid, according to his eternal and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49055:16"/>immutable purpoſe, and the ſecret Counſel and good pleaſure of his Will, hath choſen in Chriſt unto everlaſting Glory, out of his meer free grace and love, without any fore-ſight of Faith or good Works, or perſeverance in either of them, or any other thing in the Creature, as Cauſes or Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons moving him thereunto, and all to the praiſe of his glorious Grace. 6 As God hath appointed the Elect unto Glory, ſo hath he by the Eternal and moſt free purpoſe of his Will, fore-ordained all the means thereunto; wherefore they who are Elected, being fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> are redeemed by Chriſt, are effectually called unto Faith in Chriſt by his Spirit working in due ſeaſon, are Juſtifyed, Adopted and Sanctifyed, and kept by his power through Faith unto Salvation: neither are any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther redeemed by Chriſt, Effectually, Juſtifyed, Adopted, Sanctifyed &amp; Saved, but the Elect only. 7. The reſt of mankind God was pleaſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the unſearchable Counſel of his own Will, whereby he extendeth or with holdeth mercy as he pleaſeth, for the glory of his Sovereign power over his Creatures, to paſs by and ordain them to Diſhonour and Wrath for their Sin, to the praiſe of his glorious Juſtice. 8. The Doctrine of this high Myſtery of Predeſtination, is to be handled with ſpecial prudence and care, that men attending the will of God revealed in his Word, and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obedience thereunto, may from the certainty of their Effectual Vocation, be aſſured of their Eternal Election. So ſhall this Doctrine afford matter of Praiſe, Reverence and Admiration, and of humility, diligence, and abundance of conſolation
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49055:17"/>to all that ſincerely obey the Goſpel.</q> Let any man make it appear that this is not the unanimous Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that they teach any other Doctrine diſagreeing hereunto, <hi>Et erit mihi magnus Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs I have oft heard, how ſome upon all occaſions, have bitterly run at <hi>the Doctrine of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination,</hi> as if none maintained ſuch a Doctrine but we; And a <hi>Miniſter of your</hi> Iſland, <hi>called it, A damnable Doctrine:</hi> and I now juſtly wonder to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch a Character of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> from ſome, that it is <hi>contrary to the word of God, and a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Piety.</hi> Therefore I am now to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the received and approved Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> concerning <hi>Predestination,</hi> ſince the Reformation to this Day; and ſhall begin with the 39 Articles agreed upon in a Convocation, held at <hi>London</hi> 1552, in the Reign of <hi>Edw</hi> 6 and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently renewed &amp; ratifyed in the following Reigns, and continued the <hi>eſtabliſhed Doctrine</hi> of the Church to this day, which <hi>Diſsenters</hi> with ſome allowed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions ſubſcribe as their <hi>own Doctrine,</hi> as a legal qualification for our Liberty. I wiſh you would read and conſider again the 17th. Article, <hi>Viz.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination</hi> to life is the everlaſting purpoſe of God, whereby before the foundations of the World were laid, he hath conſtantly decreed by his Counſel, ſecret to us, to deliver from curſe &amp; damnation, thoſe, whom he hath choſen in Chriſt Jeſus out of mankind, and to bring them by Chriſt to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Salvation, as veſſels made to honour; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that be endued with ſo Excellent a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of God, be called according to Gods purpoſe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49055:17"/>by his Spirit working in due ſeaſon, they through Grace obey the calling, they be Juſtifyed freely, they be made Sons of God by Adoption, they be made like the Image of his only begotten Son Jeſus Chriſt, they walk religiouſly in good works, and at length by Gods mercy they attain to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting felicity. As the Godly conſideration of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> and our Election in Chriſt, is full of ſweet, pleaſant and unſpeakable comfort to Godly perſons, and ſuch as feel in themſelves the workings of the Spirit of Chriſt, mortifying the works of the fleſh, and their earthly members, and drawing up their mind to high &amp; heavenly things, as well becauſe it doth eſtabliſh and confirm their Faith of eternal Salvation, to be enjoyed through Chriſt, as becauſe it doth frequently kindle their Love towards God, ſo for curious and carnal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, lacking the Spirit of Chriſt, to have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally before their eyes, the ſentence of Gods <hi>Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> is a moſt dangerous downfall, whereby the Devil doth thruſt them either to deſperation, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wretchleſsneſs of moſt unclean living, no leſs perilous than deſperation. Furthermore we muſt receive Gods promiſes in ſuch wiſe, as they be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſet forth to us in the holy Scriptures, and and in our doings that will of God is to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, which we have expreſsly declared to us in the word of God</q> And as to the ſenſe of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, take it from the Learned of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Dr. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> in his <hi>Cygne a Cantio,</hi> pag. 16, 17. (<hi>Dr. Bridges</hi> ſtiles this, <hi>The chiefeſt Article of the Church in Doctrine.</hi>) Mr <hi>Thomas Rogers</hi> in his <hi>Analyſis,</hi> bound up formerly with the Articles. Dr. <hi>Thyſins</hi> in his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49055:18"/>Commentary on <hi>Lambeth Articles,</hi> ſully explain this Article, &amp; raiſe theſe concluſions from it. 1. That there is a <hi>Predeſtination</hi> of certain men to eternal Life, a preterition, predeſtination, or <hi>Reprobation</hi> of certain men unto Death. 2. That this <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is no manifeſt, no open Decree, into the grounds &amp; cauſes of which every mean capacity may dive, but a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den purpoſe, counſel or decree of God, which is kept <hi>ſecret</hi> from us. 3. That this <hi>Predeſtination</hi> to life is from <hi>Eternity.</hi> 4. That it is altogether <hi>immutable</hi> and unchangeable as God himſelf. This is the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Doctrine which all the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſubſcribe or aſſent unto at Ordination.</p>
            <p>The next demonſtration and diſcovery of the Doctrine of the Church in this point, is from the <hi>Lambeth Articles,</hi> agreed upon at <hi>Lambeth</hi> Houſe, by <hi>John</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Richard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London, Richard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bangor,</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tindall,</hi> Dean of <hi>Elie,</hi> Dr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> profeſſor of Divinity at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> with ſeveral learned Divines of the Church; with the approbation of <hi>Matthew</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>York,</hi> compoſed at firſt in Latin and ſent to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to prevent and cruſh ſome <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian</hi> Controverſies that were beginning to be raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there: yet I ſhall give you in Engliſh Four of Nine, that relate to <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> never yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached or rejected by the Church, as inconſiſtent with the 39 Articles, but inſerted in the <hi>Ireland</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, and allowed of in the conference at <hi>Hampton. Court.</hi> 
               <q>1. God from eternity hath <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> certain men unto Life, certain men he hath Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated, or reprobated unto Death. 2. The moving and efficient cauſe of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> unto
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49055:19"/>Life, is not the fore ſight of Faith or Perſeverance, or good works, or of any thing in the perſons Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated, but only in the good will and pleaſure of God. 3. There is a <hi>Predeſtinate number</hi> of Predeſtinate, which can neither be augmented nor diminiſhed. 4. <hi>Thoſe who are not Predestinated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation are neceſsarily damned for their Sins.</hi>
               </q> This is more plain and particular, than any thing I have heard taught by <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and yet it is the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Teſtimony from that Church for <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destination,</hi> is the Articles of <hi>Ireland,</hi> agreed upon by the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, and the Clergy of that Kingdom in a Convocation, held at <hi>Düblin,</hi> 1615. &amp; ſeeing they were <hi>Engliſh Divines,</hi> and a part of the <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> under one King, they were received, approved and licenſed by the Government, as agreeable to the 39. Articles, and alſo thoſe of <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth;</hi> therefore I ſhall record out of them what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> or the <hi>Decrees</hi> of God.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 11 God from all eternity did by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Counſel, ordain whatſoever in time ſhould come to paſs, yet ſo as thereby no violence is offered to the wills of the reaſonable Creatures, and neither the <hi>Liberty</hi> nor <hi>Contingency</hi> of <hi>Second cauſes</hi> is taken away; but eſtabliſhed rather.</p>
               <p n="12">12. By the ſame eternal Counſel, God hath <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> ſome unto Life, and <hi>Reprobated</hi> ſome unto Death, of both which there is a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, known only to God, which can neither he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed nor diminiſhed.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Predestination unto Life,</hi> is the everlaſting purpoſe of God, whereby before the foundations of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49055:20"/>the World were laid, he hath conſtantly decreed in his Secret Counſel, to deliver from curſe and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, thoſe whom he hath choſen in Chriſt, out of mankind, and to bring them by Chriſt to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Salvation, as veſſels made unto honour.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The cauſe moving God to <hi>Predeſtinate,</hi> is not the fore-ſeeing of Faith, or Perſeverance, or Good Works, or of any thing in the perſons Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated, but only the good pleaſure of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for all things being ordained for the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Glory, and his Glory being to appear, both in the works of his Mercy &amp; Juſtice, it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good unto his heavenly wiſdom, to chooſe out a certain number toward whom he would extend his undeſerved Mercy, leaving the reſt to be Spectacles of his Juſtice.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Such as are <hi>Predestinated</hi> unto Life, be called according to Gods purpoſe, his Spirit working in due ſeaſon, and through Grace they obey the call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they be Juſtifyed freely, they be made Sons of God by Adoption, they be made like the Image of his only begotten Son Jeſus Chriſt, they walk reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly in good Work, and at length b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Mercy they attain to everlaſting felicity; but ſuch as are not <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> to Salvation, ſhall finally be condemned for their Sins.</p>
               <p n="16">16. The Godly conſideration of <hi>Predestination,</hi> and our <hi>Election</hi> in Chriſt, is full of ſweet, pleaſant, &amp; unſpeakable comfort to Godly perſons, &amp; ſuch as feel in themſelves the working of the Spirit of Chriſt, mortifying the works of the fleſh &amp; their earthly members, and drawing up their minds to high and heavenly things, as well becauſe it doth greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49055:20"/>&amp; eſtabliſh their faith, of eternal Salvation, to be enjoyed thro' Chriſt, as becauſe it doth ſervently kindle their Love towards God; and on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſide for curious &amp; carnal perſons, lacking the Spirit of Chriſt, to have continually before their Eyes, the Sentence of Gods <hi>Predestination,</hi> is very dangerous.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This is the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of Ireland,</hi> &amp; ſo exactly agreeable to the 39 Articles, &amp; thoſe of <hi>Lambeth,</hi> that I need ſay no more of them.</p>
            <p>Another diſcovery of the Doctrine of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is from the Suffrages of the <hi>five Repreſentatives</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> at the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> Dr. <hi>Carleton</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chichester,</hi> Dr. <hi>Samuel Ward</hi> publick Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity profeſſor at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Dr. <hi>Davenant</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Satisbury,</hi> Dr. <hi>Balcanquel</hi> Dean of <hi>Richester,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Thomas Goad,</hi> who were called and aſſembled to nip <hi>Arminianiſm</hi> in the bud: and they being Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated &amp; ſent by the Supream Authority in the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; their Suffrages as recorded in the publick Acts of that Synod, and by Dr. <hi>Ward,</hi> in his <hi>Suffragium Britannorum,</hi> are to be found &amp; were then received &amp; approved, at the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhould it not appear a wonder and be a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe to the <hi>hearers,</hi> tho' the <hi>Preachers</hi> cannot be Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of it; that the <hi>Common Prayer Book,</hi> the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary &amp; univerſal Book of their Devotion ſhould give its Suffrage and bear its teſtimony for <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> or <hi>Election,</hi> which upon a more ſtrict obſervation all ſhall find? In the Collect for <hi>All Saints Day,</hi> it begins, <hi>Almighty God, who haſt knit together thine</hi> Elect <hi>in one communion, and fellowſhip in the mystical Body of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> If God has an <hi>Elected</hi> people, there muſt ſome be <hi>left out</hi> and <hi>paſsed by,</hi> otherwiſe there
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49055:21"/>can be no <hi>Election</hi> or <hi>Choice.</hi> In the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally taught unto Children, in Anſwer to Q. 6. It is replyed in the third place, <hi>In God the Holy Ghoſt, who Sanctifyed me, and all the Elect people of God;</hi> which plainly inſtructs us, that God <hi>chooſeth</hi> to <hi>Sanctification,</hi> and holineſs as well as to <hi>Salvation,</hi> and that all <hi>Elect ones</hi> ſhall be <hi>Sanctifyed</hi> &amp; conſequently <hi>Saved.</hi> In the <hi>burial of the Dead,</hi> in the firſt prayer after the <hi>Lords Prayer; Beſeeching thee, that it may pleaſe thee of thy gracious Goodneſs, ſhortly to accompliſh the number of thine</hi> Elect. Here is not only an <hi>Elect,</hi> but a definite and certain <hi>Number</hi> determined with God, which are not <hi>yet accompriſhed,</hi> and the number of ſuch as are left out and paſſed by, is alſo certain and determined. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Godly prayer at all times,</hi> which is added to ſome old Bibles, there is this paſſage; <hi>In that it hath pleaſed thee freely and of thine own accord, to</hi> Elect <hi>and chooſe us to Salvation before the beginning of the World</hi> This is plain language, and in the Books of <hi>Devotion,</hi> and even thoſe who little thought <hi>Common Prayer</hi> favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> which they oft called a <hi>Damnable Doctrine,</hi> and is ſo particular, for a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſome of your Neighbours have aſſerted, <hi>contrary to the word of God, and a great diſcouragement to Piety;</hi> So that I wonder how the <hi>Oxford Oath</hi> of <hi>Aſsent &amp; Conſent</hi> ſhall reliſh for the future, wherein men Swear, <hi>That nothing is contained in the Book of Cannons, Ordination of Biſhops, and Common Prayer, contrary to the word of God,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Predeſtination</hi> is found in one of them.</p>
            <p>We call in alſo to witneſs for us, the <hi>Homilies</hi> of the Church, which appear to be principally the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Doctrine thereof, for the moſt part compoſed by the Arch-biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> who ſealed among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49055:21"/>more, this and other truths, with his Blood. It were too tedious to tranſcribe all here, but I ſhall give a paſſage or two, to engage Readers to be more at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive and obſervant for the ſuture. Therefore in the 2d part about <hi>p.</hi> 160. <q>God of his mercy &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial favour, towards them whom he hath appointed to everlaſting Salvation, hath ſo offered his Grace eſpecially, and they have ſo received it fruitfully, that altho' by reaſon of their ſinful living out ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they ſeemed before to have been the Children of wrath &amp; perdition, yet now the Spirit of God might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ily working in them unto the obedience of Gods will, that they are the undoubted Children of God, appointed unto everlaſting Life: for the Good fruit is not the cauſe the tree is good: but the tree muſt firſt be good, before it can bring forth good fruit.</q> This &amp; much more may be found in both parts for confirmation of this Doctrine of <hi>Predeſtination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I refer you alſo to a <hi>Church of England Catechiſm,</hi> enjoyned by K <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. to all Schoolmaſters, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Children throughout the Kingdom, wherein it is aſſerted, <q>That the faithful were ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen, <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> and appointed to everlaſting life, before the world was made, &amp; that the cauſe of our Juſtification &amp; Salvation, is the goodneſs &amp; love of God, whereby he choſe us, before he made the world.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot omit certain Queſtions &amp; Anſwers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> publiſhed by <hi>Robert Parker,</hi> &amp; continued to be bound in with your Bibles, until the year 1615. I ſhall give you a hint thereof in two or three Queſtions, relating to <hi>Predeſtination.</hi> 
               <q>Q Are not all <hi>ordained to eternal Life?</hi> A. Some are <hi>Veſsels of Wrath,</hi> ordained to Deſtruction, as others are
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49055:22"/>
                  <hi>Veſsels of Mercy,</hi> prepared for Glory. Q How ſtandeth it with Gods <hi>Juſtice,</hi> that ſome are <hi>appointed to Damnation?</hi> A. Very well, becauſe all men have in themſelves Sin, which deſerveth no leſs, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the mercy of God is wonderful, in that he Vouched to ſave ſome of that ſinful race, and to bring them to the knowledge of the Truth Q. But how ſhall I know I am <hi>ordained to eternal</hi> life? A. By the motions of Spiritual Life, which belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth only to the Children of God.</q> I might enlarge with variety of Teſtimonies in favour of this Doctrine, from the Learned and Godly in all the paſt Reigns, from the Reformation down ward; and ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with that honourable, and venerable Suffrage of <hi>Primate <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> in his <hi>Sum and ſubſtance of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion,</hi> which for the Satisfaction of all, I ſhall deliver in his own words. <q>Q What are the parts of <hi>Predeſtination?</hi> A <hi>Election</hi> &amp; <hi>Reprobation</hi> Q. What is <hi>Election?</hi> A. Tis the everlaſting <hi>Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> or fore appointment of certain Angels and men unto everlaſting life and bleſſedneſs, for the praiſe of Gods glorious Grace and Goodneſs. Q What is <hi>Reprobation?</hi> A. It is the eternal fore-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of certain Angels &amp; men unto everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſhonour and Deſtruction, God of his own free will determining to paſs them by, refuſe, &amp; caſt them off, and for ſin condemn and puniſh them, with eternal Death.</q> And to theſe you may add moſt <hi>Church of England</hi> Books common among us; as alſo that common Book almoſt in every Family, <hi>The Practice of Piety,</hi> So it is to be hoped you will not adventure to ſay, the <hi>Church of Scotland</hi> holds any other <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> than what is the Doctrine of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49055:22"/>
               <hi>Church of England;</hi> or that it is <hi>contrary to the word of God, and a great diſcouragement to Piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am very unwilling to engage in a further contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy about this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſo fully handled, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently vindicated already, leſt I ſhould engage ſome of your Iſland in a moſt <hi>unnatural War,</hi> againſt their own <hi>Mother Church:</hi> and ſhould it not be a Paradox to <hi>Barbados,</hi> to hear of a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> taking up the Cudgels, in defence of a <hi>fundamental eſtabliſhed Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,</hi> againſt a <hi>Son,</hi> a <hi>Member,</hi> and a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Engliſh Church? And ſeeing one hath been pleaſed to run upon Quaeries on this occaſion, I am obliged to entertain you with a <hi>few,</hi> concerning the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Doctrine, in behalf both of Diſſenters and the <hi>Church of England.</hi> The Quaeries are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether God be not an abſolute &amp; Sovereign power &amp; being, having infinitely a greater &amp; more illimited and boundleſs Authority, over the higheſt and beſt of his creatures, without being controuled by, or accountable to them; I ſay, more than the <hi>Potter has over the clay,</hi> he frames at his pleaſure, for honourable &amp; diſhonourable uſes &amp; ſervices?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether God from an infinite and eternal knowledge <hi>knows infallibly,</hi> the certain &amp; determined number of them that ſhall be <hi>Saved,</hi> and ſhall be <hi>Damned,</hi> which number ſhall never be encreaſed, neither can be diminiſhed?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether it is God of <hi>his own will, free grace</hi> and goodneſs, that makes the difference between <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether the immutable and <hi>unchangeable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees</hi> of God, in the execution of them, rob the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its <hi>liberty,</hi> in acting or doing?</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49055:23"/>
            <p n="5">5. Whether a Sinner without the <hi>ſpecial and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Grace</hi> of God, can repent, believe, regenerate, and ſave himſelf?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether God can be accounted <hi>unjuſt</hi> for <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a part,</hi> while he might juſtly have <hi>damned the whore World</hi> for their Sir?</p>
            <p n="7">7 Whether God deſigned the <hi>Salvation</hi> of any without <hi>holineſs, faith</hi> and <hi>repentance,</hi> or the <hi>damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of any without fore-running <hi>Sin,</hi> final unbelief, and impenitence?</p>
            <p n="8">8 Whether God abſolutely and unchangeably determined with himſelf the <hi>period</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of our dayes in this life?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether God the <hi>Father</hi> determined from all eternity, to <hi>ſend his own Son</hi> our Saviour, into the World. &amp; all his particular Sufferings in the World?</p>
            <p n="10">10 Whether we ſhould decry or diſown, thoſe great &amp; tranſcending Myſteries of God's Counſel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we cannot reach, nor comprehend them with our ſhallow and narrow Capacities, or carnal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions?</p>
            <p>If any intend to give any reſolution to theſe ten Quaeries, I hope I need not caution them againſt ſuch things, as in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ringe, and may tend to impeach the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Sovereignty, and Prerogative of Heaven, or condemn their own Church. And I aſſure my ſelf, they will not revive again thoſe groundleſs, ſilly and inconſequential Allegations, vulgarly heaped up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Doctrine; which have been long ſince <hi>unſwered, confuted, and overthrown.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49055:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
